A Finding Aid to the Abraham Rattner and Esther Gentle Papers, 1891-1986, in the Archives of American Art AAA.rattabra
Archives of American Art
- Photographs, 1891-1970s, undated; Series 19; (boxes 27-29; 1.6 linear ft.)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; 19.11
    - Miscellaneous, undated; (7 folders) (Box 28 (hol), Reel unfilmed)
    - Scenes from Beggar's Opera, undated (Box 29 (sol), Reel unfilmed)
- Works of Art by Rattner, 1912-1914, 1940-1967, undated; Series 20; (box 30, ovs 37-44; 2.4 linear ft.)
  The works of art by Abraham Rattner represent a cross-section of his career. His very early work includes water color studies, sketches, and caricatures drawn for his high school yearbook. In addition, studies for some of his paintings, miscellaneous sketches, a sketchbook with studies for his series Le Boef, E'corchés, watercolor studies for The Boxing Match as well as color studies are present here.
  - Early sketches and studies (see also ov 37 for senior yearbook drawings and ov 38 for watercolor studies), 1912, undated (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Sketch from U.S.A. trip with Henry Miller, 1940 (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Ink/watercolor drawings and studies (see also ovs 39, 40 and 41), undated (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Miscellaneous sketches, undated (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Portrait studies of Percival Goodman, M. Solz, Rabbi Bricher, 1956 (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Sketches, undated; (4 folders) (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Small paintings, undated (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Drawing for A. Leepa's book The Challenge of Modern Art, undated (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Sketches of Esther Gentle, 1956 (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Sketchbook, undated (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Le Boef, E'corchés (Studies in the Meat Market), undated; (3 folders) (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Watercolor studies The Boxing Match, undated (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Color palates, 1940s, undated (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Studies of clowns, [1958] (Box 42 (ov), Reel 5277)
  - Studies for old shoes, [1967] (Box 43 (ov), Reel 5277)
  - Charts of color changes and comparative color reliabilities, 1943-1944, 1950-1951 (Box 44 (ov), Reel 5277)
- Works of Art by Others, undated; Series 21; (box 30, ov 45; 6 folders)
  Art work by Max Weber, Ken Buryd, and unknown artists are represented in this subseries in addition to a painting of Virginia by Henry Miller. Genres include paintings, prints, and drawings.
  - Ken Buryd, undated (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Henry Miller, undated (Box 45 (ov), Reel 5277)
  - Max Weber, undated (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Unknown artist, undated (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Air-Conditioned Nightmare frontice piece by unknown artist, undated (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - Rodin prints (2), undated (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
  - The Bee Tree by C.I. Sprout, Brother David, undated (Box 30 (hol), Reel 5277)
- Bettina Bedwell Papers, 1932-1947, undated; Series 22; (box 31; 0.4 linear ft.)
  Rattner kept Bedwell's diary, passport, her writings such as a poem that she wrote to him entitled Abe, her fashion articles, a typescript for a book that she was writing entitled Fashion Correspondent, her fashion sketches, correspondence, death certificate and plans for her funeral.
  - Biographical notes, undated (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Passport, identity card, French visa, 1932-1939 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Diary, 1944 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - United Press Club membership card, 1945 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Writings, poem "Abe,", 1936 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Writings, fashion articles, 1940 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Writings, Paris Correspondent typescripts for chapters 1-4, undated; (8 folders) (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Paris Correspondent drafts and notes, undated (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Color fashion drawings, undated (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Fashion sketches, 1940s, undated; (6 folders) (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Correspondence, 1928-1947, undated (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Notes, undated (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Itemized expense reports, 1939-1940 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Syndicate paychecks, 1947 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Reviews of book Yellow Dusk, 1937 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Funeral, 1947 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Death certificate, 1947 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Obituary notices, 1947 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Funeral flower cards, 1947 (Box 31, Reel unfilmed)
  - Flower and get well soon cards, 1947 (Box 31, Reel unfilmed)
- Esther Gentle Papers, 1921-1984, undated; Series 23; (boxes 31-32; 1.3 linear ft.)
  Though Esther Gentle is represented throughout the collection, papers belonging solely to her are found in this series. Materials include: the birth certificate for her son Bernard Mozen, her marital history, a draft of her will, her application for the Guggenheim Memorial Fellowship, her resume, correspondence, notes, art work, art expenses, as well as papers regarding her business Esther Gentle Reproductions such as order books, sales records, inventories, catalog mock-ups, correspondence, and invoices. Diary entries, notes and writings contain detailed journal-type recollections and expressions of very personal psychological and emotional issues that Gentle dealt with, including the process of grieving and coming to terms with Rattner's death.
  - Birth certificate of Bernard Mozon, 1921 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Marital history, notes and certificate, 1930, 1938, 1949 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - U.S. Government grant application, 1949 (Box 31, Reel unfilmed)
  - French drivers license, 1951 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Draft of will, 1964 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Résumé, 1965 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - French visa, 1965 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Passport application, 1966 (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Guggenheim fellowship application, undated (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Partial transcipt of newspaper interview, undated (Box 31, Reel 5277)
  - Inventory of art work, undated (Box 31, Reel unfilmed)
  - Photographs of Esther Gentle, undated (Box 31, Reel unfilmed)
  - Printed material, 1965-1967, 1981, undated (Box 31, Reel unfilmed)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1984, undated; (10 folders) (Box 31, Reel 5277-5278)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1983, undated (Box 31, Reel unfilmed)
  - Notes, 1965, 1974, 1981; (3 folders) (Box 31, Reel 5278)
  - Notebooks, miscellaneous notes and sketches (6), undated; (2 folders) (Box 31, Reel 5278)
  - Notes and writings, undated (Box 31, Reel 5278)
  - Notes and writings, 1961-1983, undated (Box 31, Reel unfilmed)
  - Diary entries, 1950, 1929-1980 (Box 31, Reel 5278)
  - Death of Gentle's brother (Box 31, Reel 5278)
  - Notebooks, undated; (2 folders) (Box 32, Reel 5278)
  - Brooklyn Hebrew Home and Hospital for the Aged, notes, 1942 (Box 32, Reel 5278)
  - Brooklyn Hebrew Home and Hospital for the Aged, drawings, 1942; (2 folders) (Box 32, Reel 5278)
  - Brooklyn Hebrew Home and Hospital for the Aged, photographs, 1943 (Box 32, Reel 5278)
  - List of Gentle's sculpture, undated (Box 32, Reel 5278)
  - Artwork, sketches, undated; (3 folders) (Box 32, Reel unfilmed)
  - Art expenses, 1945, 1957; (2 folders) (Box 32, Reel unfilmed)
  - Esther Gentle Reproductions exhibition materials, undated (Box 32, Reel 5278)
  - Esther Gentle Reproductions order books, 1947-1948 (Box 32, Reel 5278)
  - Esther Gentle Reproductions sales records, 1951, undated (Box 32, Reel 5278)
  - Esther Gentle Reproductions inventories, (2 folders) (Box 32, Reel 5279)
  - Esther Gentle Reproductions, photographs of store, undated (Box 32, Reel 5279)
  - Esther Gentle Reproductions catalog mock-up, undated (Box 32, Reel 5279)
  - Esther Gentle Reproductions catalog designs, undated (Box 32, Reel 5279)
  - Esther Gentle Reproductions correspondence, 1946-1969, undated; (10 folders) (Box 32, Reel 5279)
  - Esther Gentle Reproductions order books, [1951-1952]; (2 folders) (Box 32, Reel 5279)
  - Esther Gentle Reproductions invoices, 1951-1954; (4 folders) (Box 32, Reel 5279)
- Allen Leepa Papers, 1952-1969, undated; Series 24; (box 32; 8 folders)
  This small series contains writings, correspondence, legal documents and Leepa's curriculum vitae from 1969.
  - Excerpt from The American Way, 1952 (Box 32, Reel 5279)
  - Memo to request additional research time, 1958 (Box 32, Reel 5279)
  - Proposal for film project, undated (Box 32, Reel 5279)
  - Curriculum vitae, [1969] (Box 32, Reel 5279)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 32, Reel 5279)
  - Illustrations for The Challenge of Modern Art, undated (Box 32, Reel 5279)
  - Contract for book Understanding Modern Art (later called The Challenge of Modern Art), 1947 (Box 32, Reel 5279)
  - Legal agreement regarding film Genesis of an Idea: Abraham Rattner, 1965 (Box 32, Reel 5279)